you
the star the star of yesterday's lecture
was the growl fixed-point theorem
it said that if you have a match from a
bolt in itself remember that this is the
closed ball so it has boundary contains
a boundary and the map is continuous
must have a fixed point and we used it
from an easier but ultimately more
powerful fix for theorem due to less
ships less sheds a peek applies to only
close situations in other words when
there is no boundary Brava
of course the problem involves a
boundary we have to resolve a trick and
we shall see many applications of this
today but before we start let me make a
comment about white and black I have
seen several times
Koreans aside for colleagues writing on
the blackboard do this do this do this
and say black dot white dot
and I've always wondered about this why
huh but why but yes but many people say
this is black and this is why really
yes this is a cup of coffee
not cup of milk because this is supposed
to be black hug the surface of coffee
then happy committee come the committee
as you know consists of many many many
molecules tiny cakes
for example this is one this is another
this is another the Nagas and so what's
molecules well start cooking
do you know what it is the stirrer
Lumiere so you put the spoon and then
you when you do this maybe this molecule
moves there
this is like you moves there this
molecule moves there and this molecule
might go there and this molecule might
go there and so what it will move around
but this motion is essentially
continuous what I mean is if you have
two neighbor molecules they go fairly
close to each other they don't separate
like this
when you stir at least let's assume that
it's a continuous process and we are not
introducing any discontinuity and
besides I don't know how into this
continue so stir the coffee and the
molecules and as I indicate here move to
some new positions all the wedges
fear which is the consequence of Rolla
well is that the exists some molecule
which finds itself in its original
position and maybe you should say what
sir
well I guess what exists a molecule can
be only one which ok because after being
stirred that's clear that's because
there must be in this continuous mapping
of the disk itself there must be a
molecule which comes back to its
original positions because it's a
continuous map from the disk itself
before and after there is a fixed point
that means that he comes back
next example I couldn't find the map of
using work but you have probably seen a
map of this region Muizenberg Cape Town
and so on okay well if you look at the
map and put it on the floor and let's
say that you find
Muizenberg mountain on the map the top
of the user Berg mountain have you been
to the top of the museum Rock Mountain
who has not yet been to the top of
Museum work mountain maybe we should all
go and anyway topic muizenberg mountain
on the map well look at the point on the
ground directly underneath the point on
the map okay so on the map it says top
amuse remark on the peak of muizenberg
Martin
but the point directly underneath the
real point on the ground is usually not
the peak of the museum at Martin right
do you see what I'm saying it's too
confused if I take the map to the peak
of muizenberg Martin and put it there of
course the point underneath is a few
people music Bergman so usually the
point on the map is not the same it
doesn't represent the point on the
ground the real potent ground which is
directly under underneath it on the map
however Brava says the forward
dr. Maccabee zimberg anywhere in New
Zealand
so what I do is the drama
theorem
the exists a point on the map that
represents exactly the point that
represents the point on the ground
directly underneath the sun's mysteries
but what is this this is because this is
a map of muizenberg and let's say
although it is very small this is the
actual Muizenberg okay
now the actual ISM work might be
complicated shape but that shape is
homeomorphic to a disk so we have a
mapping from a disk to inside itself by
browser there must be a fixed point but
fixed point means that there must be a
point which did not move which means
that the point on the map is exactly
above the point that it represents on
the ground
interesting
more examples who in this class has
learnt or seeing game theory anybody
have you heard of the game theory you
have again theory I would have to say is
a very easy subject well okay there are
some parts that are difficult I should
mention these in a moment but overall
it's a very easy subject you can learn
it if we have time I can teach it in
about one hour now it's true I teach
games giving one hour in Cambridge and
everyone understands everything but but
it is quite useful for example economics
if you study economics in the
mathematical way and it's very
fashionable
there are lots and lots of economists
who study mathematical aspect of
economics game theory is one of the main
tools of mathematical economics and also
in sort of policy making and planning
sorry sorry yeah and so on game theory
is very popular it's an easy thing now
there are difficult parts of game theory
not always difficult but that not all is
easy but the difficult part it turns out
is encapsulated in something called Nash
equilibrium theorem so when two
typically reason for delay and I play
some game naturally although I wants to
do her best and I want to do my best and
the situation where you know although
they have some strategy and I have some
strategy and we cannot do any better in
other words if I change my strategy a
little bit then auto rate immediately
has an advantage and conversely if she
changes her strategy a little bit it
immediately that gives me an advantage
that situation is call
the equilibrium in game theory is that
okay so if both players or the LAN I are
very intelligent we change the
equilibrium strategies we don't choose
anything else okay now it's not clear
that in any game with reasonable
hypothesis such an equilibrium exists
and it turns out that this equilibrium
is probabilistic
but anyway it's not clear that such an
equilibrium exists but the theorem due
to Nash is that it does so I should
first say it and then explain a little
more what's going on the brow a fixed
point theorem was used by in game 3
to prove the existence of a Nash
equilibrium Nash na Sh
and this was done in possibly the
shortest PhD thesis in history Nash was
a graduate student at Princeton in the
late 1940s and he in fact primarily he
was a German
he worked in geometry and he left
fantastic deep results in geometry he
still alive
by the way but one day he was interested
by von Neumann in game theory so he
thought about it and he proved this
absolutely fundamental theorem in game
theory and this is the difficult part of
game theory and for which he received
the Nobel Prize in Economics in 1994
have you seen the movie A Beautiful Mind
Nash is that man now it turns out that
the core of this proof is brother
fixed-point theorem unfortunately
because we got much time in three weeks
I cannot devote an hour to teach you
game theory and show you how brower
implies Nash equilibrium but I'd like to
encourage those of you who are
interested in looking up for example
Wikipedia and so forth to teach yourself
game theory and under
but naturally Reuben is and this follows
from the graphic sponsor another curious
remark although this is outside the
course
braava implies the existence Nash
equilibrium it turns out only as far as
I know it's not mentioned anywhere in
the literature that the converse is true
if you assume that any game you have to
put some hypothesis but any reasonable
game has a Nash equilibrium if you take
that theorem as a consequence you can
reduce graphics point 0 data so those
two things are equivalent interesting
stage ok if you're interested in the
converse I can explain you but in order
for you to understand the Congress you
have know what game series okay now I
shall devote the rest of this lecture to
a major application of graphics points
here those were small applications
entertaining though they were well the
game theory application is a major
application because it became huge Nobel
Prize and he received Nobel Prize partly
because she knew topology that's very
nice
yes because he he was courageous enough
to use a tool that nobody else was using
so what people do is to keep using the
tools that everyone else is used well if
you do that you're competing with
everyone else and what are the chances
that you win against a thousands and
tens of thousands of other people but if
you do something different you have a
much better chance okay
so application this is going to be
applied to probability be precise to
what is called finite Markov chains
please raise your hands who has heard of
Markov chain who has never heard a
Markov chain and
have you heard of marketing or have you
not heard of Mataji then you should say
one or the other use the raise your hand
when you when asked who has not heard
knowledge so finite Markov chain I shall
explain what Markov chain is I hope you
understand what it is but if you don't
don't worry you can fall asleep until
the end of the lecture Markov chain is
the most important of random or
stochastic processes when you learn
probability you first begin by learning
Oh what's the probability that for
example when you toss a coin heads
appears of course it's one half okay
everyone knows that you don't have to
learn probability to do this and then
you do one more complicate things you
learn various theorems such as law large
numbers central limit theorem and so on
but what is really interesting in
probability goes happens be be honest in
other words random processes and
stochastic processes when nature or some
phenomenon evolves in a probabilistic
way not deterministic with lots and lots
of uncertainties how does that evolution
work probabilistically that's stochastic
processes and markov chains are the best
kind of stochastic process that's the
kind that everyone has studied and it's
best understood and it appears most
often in applications of Markov chain
roughly speaking it says the following
let's say that some system phenomenon
can be in many different states you
might be reminded of if you are taking
statistical mechanics but you're talking
about instead Mac there's no that's not
an accident because this is football
stats go mechanics in some sense a
special case of the discussion so you
have many many different possible states
in which
system can find itself and as usual for
Jamaica topologist we shall draw a
picture and this is a collection of all
the different states interesting idea so
for example if you have some block of
material yeah so you can say all in this
state the temperature is 45 degrees and
the pressure is 25 and Pascal and in
this state the temperature is minus 15
degrees and the pressure is zero Pascal
in this state the temperature is 200
degrees and the pressure is 480 Pascal
and so on you know what I mean different
states so it's an abstract picture but
it's a fictional dress and suppose that
we have some evolution of the state
which take evolving time is such
changing in time and say that it can go
from this state to this state but it's
not a big a holistic process so it can
also go from here to here or it can jump
from here to here okay
and so how do we decide we try to go
well let's say that I change from this
state this state with probability 1/2
this steady state will probably 1 6 and
this type of the state will probably
one-third okay
the total is 1 if I'm not mistaken so
that becomings or that design that
describes the probabilistic evolution ok
so it changes from this steady state
more often than from this state to this
state and so and then you can draw these
arrows all over the place so it can go
this way can go this way maybe this is
also communicating and and so on
ok and then you might have something
like this you might have something like
this in who knows what's going
so this way and this way
you understand the idea so all of these
have probabilities and also you might
actually have a probability for staying
at the same state okay
that's indicated by the arrow that goes
like this and so in fact in many of
those this in this case for example at
this point the probability of staying
the same state is 0 but you might have
lots of other states where you stay at
the same state and so on okay
is that clear so here I meant good try
to move to this day and so on so that's
a Markov chain what we do is you assume
that you are in some state and then you
say oh and then you know you have the
probability of being in this state in
this state in this state business at the
next step and then you say oh and then
they all jump and now you have a given
probability distribution of being which
state and so on okay
another way of thinking about the same
thing is the following suppose that you
have lots and lots of but what can you
think of a can you think of a very small
animal huh rabbit okay
Monday lacks rabbits okay let's think of
millions of rabbits and let's say that I
put those rabbits in different states
and suppose that I could say a lot of
rabbits here fewer rabbits here quite a
lot veronik see a few Arabic see are an
enormous number
and so on okay I mean each of those
states so the distribution of rabbits
tells you the distribution of the
probabilities of being the various
states all right and then you say pom
and you ask all the rabbits in this
state
yeah so maybe they're two thousand
rabbits here to jump over here with
probability 1 1/2 over here with
probability 1/3 jump here with probably
1/6 or simply say half of the rabbits
asked to go here
one-third here 1/6 here and so on okay
and from all the states order of its
obedient because rabbits obedient and
also when you say they all jump that
gives you a different distribution of
rabbits in different states okay so
that's the distribution of rabbits after
one step and then you do it again they
all jump after two steps and so forth is
that clear
okay so that's a Markov chain and it
turns out that this model simple though
it is is extremely applicable and this
kind of picture that depicts all the
states is called the state space space
of states if you like and let's say that
you want to label the states so I'm
going to label the states by some number
1 2 and so on up to M
different states that's instead number
one you might have a temperature of 40
degrees and pressure of 23 Pascal and so
in different different factors for the
different states and let's denote by P
sub I of T the probability of being in
state number label I at time T and key I
shall assume is discrete that's what I
meant by pump pump pump pump I do blow
up traffic and then all of these radix
boom jump at the same time so T's
discrete times discreet well how do we
describe those jumps mathematically
there is a very elegant way of doing it
let us call G a certain matrix we shall
call it the generator or if you read the
trunk the probably little chap often
it's called transition matrix this
matrix is going to be M by M and the
entry of this matrix g IJ IJ entry of
this matrix is simply if I be the
probability of jumping from state J to
stay I is that okay for example you
might have only two states this is state
1 this is stage 2 and state 1 to state 1
is 1/3 and 2/3 and in here you jump with
property 1 and you stay with root 0 okay
so it is a Markov chain and so what you
see is the following this is I J that's
1 1 so how with my property do I stay
jump from 1 to 1 it's 1 by 3 for third
with what probability do I jump from
sorry so it from J to I so here it's the
entry to 1 so with what probability
device and do I jump from 2 to 1 with 1
yes
I'm 1 sorry to 1 so from what
probability with what property do I jump
from 1 to 2 here this is 2/3 and this is
0 that's how you write ok now if you do
that it's clear that the following takes
place what is
P 1 P 2 and so on TM of 1 how do I
calculate that lets regard it as a
vector well it's simply equal to it
turns out gee this matrix applied to P 1
at 0 p.m. at 0 because the probability
of being at P 1 at time 1 is simply
equal to the weighted sum of various
probabilities at the previous step
together with the weights corresponding
to with what property are jumping into
state 1 okay is that clear so that's
what it is and you can imagine what's
going to happen P 1 at time T 2 please
remember that this dial is the time and
the index is the level the state is
equal to G and apply to P 1 at time 1 2
p-m at time 1 but we know what this
vector at time 1 is is this so it is
equal to G squared I calculate the
matrix squared
bless you up and apply it to the
probability distribution vector at time
0 and so you understand already that in
general p-m at time T extinct T 1
p.m. at time t is equal to what is it G
to the T power of course and apply to
the initial distribution which at all
this vector the initial is traditional
for audience whistles this curve is
shortened from this division okay thus
the analysis of the Markov chain all the
information about metal chain is
contained in this matrix generator
matrix 26 G and the entire mathematics
of Markov chain is about analyzing what
holds the product Oh G how do you
calculate the products of matrices the
best way to do it is in an eigenbasis
after diagonalizing the matrix and then
the products are very easy to calculate
so that's how see my culture